Let's now take a look at how neural networks actually work.
In general, the simplest version of the neural network
has one layer, and you can think of it
as multiple regression algorithms running simultaneously,
one for each of the classes we're trying to predict.
So here's a simple case where we're
trying to take the same data, which
will be our x inputs plus the set to 1 bias.
We will, of course, have weights times each of these.
And there is, of course, going to be
a weight from each of the inputs to each of our activation units
or essentially regression algorithms.
Essentially, this one will predict class 3.
This one will predict class 2.
This one will predict class 1.
And this will be using the familiar one
versus rest configuration, where essentially each
of these activation units gets trained
to differentiate between things that are part of its class
and are not.
And the hope is that every instance
will show up with exactly one value set, for instance,
010, to predict class 2.
This is the simplest form of network.
It is single layer.
And it's really just a generalization
of the familiar techniques that we've seen for regression.
We can train it much the same way.
Of course, things can get more interesting
in that we can create multilayer or deeper networks.
When people talk about deep neural networks,
that's really what they're saying.
There are multiple so-called hidden layers in between.
Now, the interesting thing about a deep neural network
is that training, which, of course, involves
putting inputs along here and giving feedback
on the error or the loss with respect to predicted class
versus actual class, this training will separately
set weights for this individual activation unit,
this one and this one.
And ultimately, each of them will learn essentially
to predict an intermediate feature,
which will be different from the others
because each of our activation units
essentially starts with different random settings
for the weights.
And as you give feedback, they'll each differentiate
in different ways that are complementary.
So basically, the important thing here
is that the deep neural network actually
learns to extract meaningful features
in these hidden or intermediate layers.
Let's now go back to the case of the simple single layer
network and look at how it works in more detail.
So of course, as we already alluded to,
you're going to be training multiple of these neurons,
one for each class, on the same input.
So let's take a look at how this actually
works with an example.
We're going to have two features, x1 and x2
as our inputs.
Of course, note that that also means
we will have a bias x0 equals 1.
And we're going to build essentially two predictors,
one for the AND function.
So it should learn x1 and x2.
This is the Boolean function.
And then we will have a second one,
which learns the Boolean OR function, x1 or x2.
We're going to use a simple function called
HEAVYSIDE to be our activation function.
And that's basically going to look like this, where
it essentially gives you true or false,
depending on whether x is less than 0 or greater than
or equal to 0.
So note that this one is actually
a very particular function that usually we
don't use much in real networks because it's not
differentiable.
But for our particular example, it
makes for a simpler set of use cases.
Now, usually for real neural networks,
we're not going to use HEAVYSIDE because it's not really
suitable for gradient descent because of its stair-step
nature.
But nonetheless, it makes for a convenient example
to illustrate the principles.
So we're going to use it here.
The basic setup will then be the diagram that we see here.
So again, we can see that we have the bias, which
is also x0.
That will be value 1.
And then we are going to have a series of weights.
So we can see there's a weight vector here
that corresponds to our activation unit 1.
And there similarly will be a weight vector
along these lines, which will be for our second activation
unit.
And of course, what will happen is we will do x dot with w1
star to be our first activation unit,
and x dot w2 star to be our second activation unit.
Each of these will be what we see in the sigma here.
And then we'll apply our HEAVYSIDE function over each.
So this first one corresponds to this.
And we'll ultimately have to be x1 and x2.
The second one corresponds to here.
And we'll ultimately learn x1 or x2.
OK, so how do we actually train?
Well, we do this actually in a completely incremental way.
Essentially, we're going to take each sample, which I'll just
call x, although we might call it x sub i.
And we'll make a prediction for class j
by multiplying our input x by all of the wj's in a vector.
And of course, then we apply our activation function,
which in this case was a HEAVYSIDE.
So for our particular unit 1 that
tries to predict x1 and x2, if we're given x of 0, 1
and weights like this, of course, what we first have to do
is take our original x and add the bias.
So now we get a vector 1, 0, 1.
We multiply now our x prime by our weight vector.
And we get a value of 0.11, which is greater than 0.
So therefore, our prediction is y1 equals 1.
Now immediately, we can train.
We can update our w of j into the next round
by multiplying our error.
So in this case, y minus y hat times the value of x
times our learning rate eta, which
looks exactly like we saw with stochastic gradient descent.
And we're going to repeat this process for many rounds
or epochs.
So let's take a look at training in action.
Here, we're going to learn OR.
So this is really the activation unit number 2
from our example.
The truth table, therefore, the actual outputs
of the function for Boolean OR are as follows.
0 OR OR is 0.
Everything else is a 1.
When we initialize our neural network,
we're going to set the weights to a random set of values.
So we're going to have weight 2, 0, weight 2, 1, and weight 2,
2 in this case.
Those are for our initial bias, our x1 and our x2.
So this is our initial set of values.
Again, recall that we have three of these
because the 0th one, the initial one, is for the bias.
OK, we now start with the first input,
which will be the first entry from our truth table.
So in this case, we're training on x equals 0, 0.
Of course, the first thing we need
to do is add our bias, so a 0th element with value 1.
And now we can multiply x by w2 star, or w2.
And if we do this, it'll turn out
the product is actually 0 because we have two 0s here
and one 0 here.
Now, if we look at that, we can apply Heaviside to it.
Actually, Heaviside on 0 is 1 because Heaviside
returns 1 for anything greater than or equal to 0.
So our y hat is 1.
The actual value, the real value of y, should be 0.
So clearly, we have an error.
Now, to do our weight update, we compute delta of w2
by taking the learning rate times
the difference between the actual and predicted values
times our value of y that we tested on.
And so in this case, our learning rate
is going to be 0.01 times 0 minus 1 times 1.00.
And that will give us an update like this.
So we can see that we're going to adjust the 0th entry right
here by negative 0.1 and leave the others the same.
We will immediately do this update because, again, we're
essentially doing stochastic gradient descent here.
So now we will have a new version of our weights.
You can see the lighter blue color here
indicates what was updated.
Now we're going to train on the next value.
So again, we pull it down.
We extend it with a 1.
We multiply.
Now we get 0.69.
The heavy side on 0.69 will, again, be 1.
In this case, we have a 1 and a 1.
So the error is 0.
So the delta w2 will also be 0.
So this is good.
Now we go to the next training example.
Again, we extend it.
We multiply.
Now we get negative 0.31.
So heavy side on a negative will be 0.
In contrast, the y value is 1.
So now we have an error.
So again, eta times the difference between y and y hat
times our value of x will give us a weight update,
as we see here.
We will immediately apply it.
Now we train on 1, 1, extend it with a 1.
Do our product at 0.41.
We now do our prediction, which is a 1.
The actual value of y is actually a 1.
So we compute our update.
And in this case, there is nothing to change.
And we repeat this process through multiple epochs
until eventually we end up with the weights set
to define this particular line.
And essentially, everything to the right of that line
will be predicted as true.
Everything below will be predicted as false.
This is now the OR function.
Great.
So we saw an example with OR.
Of course, in parallel, we're doing the same thing with AND.
And in general, what we learn from the perceptron
is going to be some kind of linear decision boundary,
much like with logistic regression.
But here, we're going to predict simply the class, not
a probability of the class.
And it's guaranteed that with enough epochs,
the perceptron or the single activation unit
will converge as long as the classes are linearly separable.
How do we actually train a perceptron or simple neural
network like we saw in our examples?
Essentially, we can do this in Scikit-learn
just by calling linear model perceptron.
As usual, we would fit to the training data
and predict with the test data.
And this works pretty smoothly.
Now, perhaps surprisingly, this is
one of the few neural networks capabilities
that's built into Scikit-learn.
The developers of Scikit-learn decided early on
that they do not want to be an overall neural networks
library and instead left that to other tool kits
that we'll be talking about in a moment.
Also, perhaps interestingly, Apache Spark
only has very limited deep learning capabilities as well.
So this brings us to a new family of tools, namely
neural network frameworks.
If you follow the AI tech space at all,
you might have heard of Google's TensorFlow or perhaps
Apache MXNet or PyTorch.
All of these frameworks are actually
quite similar in spirit.
They allow you to define multiple layers
in a neural network.
And then from that, they generate
graphs of linear algebra operators working on tensors,
where tensors are essentially a generalization of me.
This style of computation actually, in many ways,
looks similar to Apache Spark's notion
of relational algebra operators over large relation.
Now, out of these different neural network frameworks,
PyTorch has recently emerged as essentially the winner.
It's the most popular, the most widely used,
and the most widely supported.
So indeed, we will be adopting PyTorch for this course.
It is, after all, the preeminent toolkit today
for deep learning, especially deep learning with GPUs.
And essentially, when you write PyTorch code,
it ultimately compiles this down into CUDA code
that runs on NVIDIA GPUs or the equivalent
for other processors.
Now, PyTorch by itself is a single GPU package,
but there is another library called Horovod,
which is useful for distributing PyTorch computations
across multiple computers and also across multiple GPUs.
So we'll be taking a look at this
as we try to scale our deep learning tech.
Now, what does a PyTorch program actually look like?
Well, here's a sketch to give you a sense of this.
Almost always, you are going to define
your neural network model
by subclassing Torch neural network module.
And essentially, you define a series of layers
by making them into member variables
and then assigning them using torch.nn.something or other,
which we'll talk about in more detail.
Sometimes you'll also define a forward propagation function,
as we see here, where you take the input,
which in this case is the input
to the entire neural network,
and then each layer computes an output
based on its operations over the input.
And that composes through multiple steps
or layers through the neural network
until you eventually return the result.
The rest of a PyTorch program
typically instantiates the model.
It calls model.train to put the model into training mode.
And then there's a loop,
which takes a series of input instances from the data,
iterates over it in many epochs,
does a computation by applying the model
to the data's X inputs,
in other words, the training instance.
That produces a series of outputs,
which are the predictions.
From that, we will take the outputs
and diff them with the actual labels
to get a loss after we apply a loss function.
Then we backward propagate the error
to adjust the weights.
And we'll talk more about this very soon.
So let's summarize what we've seen so far
about single layer neural networks.
In general, what we have is a vector of artificial neurons
that are instantiated as a single layer.
We can use this to produce one versus all classifiers
where each output makes a separate prediction.
And essentially we can train all of these
different perceptrons simultaneously
based on an update a lot like gradient descent
with a learning rate.
A perception is guaranteed to converge
for linearly separable data.
But of course, not all data is linearly separable.
And that requires us to create multi-layer networks
as we started to see in our example with PyTorch.
There are lots of frameworks besides PyTorch,
but it's going to be our focus.
And we're gonna see more about how to use it
over the next few lectures.